Guide to the Stanford University, Housing Advisory Committee, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Housing Advisory Committee, records
1968-1974
SC0175
Stanford University. Housing Advisory Committee.
1 Linear feet
Records include correspondence, notes, data, draft and final report, committee meeting minutes, newsclippings, and other documents assembled by committee chairman, Professor Gordon Wright.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Gordon Wright, 1977.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The ad hoc Housing Advisory Committee, established in 1969 by the President of Stanford University, studied the possibilities of development of low and middle income housing on Stanford land; final recommendations were submitted in 1974.
Description of the Collection
Records include correspondence, notes, data, draft and final report, committee meeting minutes, newsclippings, and other documents assembled by committee chairman, Professor Gordon Wright.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Housing Advisory Committee.; Wright, Gordon.; Clippings.; Minutes.; Public housing.; Reports.; Universities and colleges--Planning.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Low Cost Housing Committee, 1969 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    (appointed by Acting President Glasser, November 1968): Final report. (20 leaves, two xerographic copies)
  - Housing Advisory Committee Charge and Board of Trustees Approval, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pres. Kenneth Pitzer's charge to the Ad Hoc Housing Advisory Committee, 29 October 1969.; Approval of recommendation of the Board's Committee on Land Development, 13 June 1969.
  - Committee Meetings with the Board of Trustees and President Pitzer, 1969 Dec-1970 Mar (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Minutes and correspondence
  - Housing Advisory Committee Meetings, 1969 Nov 12-1970 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Minutes
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes - Report of Alan S. Maremont, 28 October 1969; Junior faculty housing survey, January 1969; E.A. Scoles Junior faculty housing proposal, November 1969; Stanford Housing Research Group
  - Correspondence, 1969 Oct-1970 Jan (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Re: Committee membership
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jan (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes - Stanford Conservation Group's report to the Committee; Minutes of a "grass roots" meeting to discuss Stanford's responsibilities in ecology and housing crises, 7 January 1970
  - Correspondence, 1970 Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes - comments from Stanford's legal advisors
  - Committee Notes and Data, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Abstracted data from P.A. Wilson's "The effect of Stanford University on the local housing market" (1969); Santa Clara County Planning Dept.'s "The housing situation: 1969, Santa Clara County" (1969)
  - #1 Draft of Committee Report, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Correspondence, data and notes
  - #1 Draft of Committee Report, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Draft (n.d.) "For discussion only" (25 leaves, typescript with annotations)
  - #2 Draft of Committee Report, 1970 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Draft (30 April 1970) (21 leaves, xerographic and typescript, with annotations)
  - #2 Draft of Committee Report, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Draft (n.d.) Second working copy? (25 leaves. Xerographic copy, with annotations)
  - Final Report of the President's Ad Hoc Housing Advisory Committee, 1970 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Professor Gordon Wright, chairman. 12 May 1970. (52 leaves. Xerographic copy. two copies.)
  - Final Report of the President's Ad Hoc Housing Advisory Committee, 1970 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Professor Gordon Wright, chairman. 12 May 1970. (75 leaves. Xerographic copy. With additional appendices.)
  - Abramovitz, Moses (Professor of Economics at Stanford), Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Comments on the Final Report of the President's Ad Hoc Committee. n.d. (6 leaves. Xerographic copy. two copies)
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes - Petition signed by 56 residents in favor of low cost housing
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jul-Nov (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Includes - Palo Alto City Managers staff report on the problem of housing in Palo Alto, July 1970; KMC draft of statement for the Palo Alto Council, July 1970; Yale University memo re: Yale's participation in community housing. (n.d.)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes - Low/Moderate Income Housing Hearing, Stanford University, July 1971
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Re: Frenchman's Terrace. Includes - Palo Alto Dept of Planning staff report on pre-zoning of terrace area (first and revised drafts, September 1972); Palo Alto Planning Commission environmental impact report.
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Palo Alto Planning Commission, 1970 Jan 7-1972 Oct 4 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mid Penninsula Citizens for Fair Housing, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Mailers
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Additional publications, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Stanford University. Proposal to Department of Housing and Urban Development ... for criteria for industrially produced housing. Technical proposal submitted by Stanford University, 1970. (137 p.); Grass Roots Writing Collective. The promised land: a grass roots report on mid-Penninsula land use. Published by Grass Roots Writing Collective in cooperation with the Stanford Chaparral. Palo Alto: 1970.